Guide to the Washington Office on Latin America Records, 1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing RL.01401
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington Office on Latin America records
1962-2020 and undated, bulk 1974-2005; 1962-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Washington Office on Latin America
RL.01401
290.5 Linear Feet
The Washington Office on Latin America is an international human rights advocacy organization headquartered in Washington D.C. The Washington Office on Latin America Records span the dates 1962 to 2008 and consist of research and project files on nearly every country in Latin America, administrative records, clippings, correspondence, and printed material, all relating to the work of the Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA), a human rights advocacy organization based in Washington D.C. WOLA partners with local organizations in Latin America and the Caribbean to raise awareness of human rights abuses in the region and to influence the foreign policy agenda of the United States government. Materials in this collection provide a rich resource for the study of politically motivated violence and other human rights abuses throughout Latin America and also document the changing political climate towards the region in Washington D.C. over nearly four decades.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Original audiovisual materials and some fragile newspapers are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before these can be accessed.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Washington Office on Latin America Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007-2010.
List of Significant Dates Related to Collection
1973 Military coup replaces the government in Paraguay
1973 Coup in Chile led by Augusto Pinochet overthrows the democratically elected government of Salvador Allende
1974 Washington Office on Latin America founded
1976 Former Chilean Ambassador Orlando Letelier and his colleague Ronnie Moffitt assassinated in a car bombing in Washington D.C.
1989 Augusto Pinochet voted out of office in first democratic election in Chile since coup
1989 U.S. forces invade Panama
1990 Panamanian dictator Manuel Noriega surrenders to authorities
1990 Governing Sandinista party voted out of office in Nicaragua
1990 Jean-Bertrand Aristide elected president of Haiti
1991 Aristide forced out of Haiti
1992 Peruvian President Alberto Fujimori dissolves Congress in "autogolpe"
1992 Peruvian Maoist group Sendero Luminoso leader Abimael Guzman captured
1995 Helms-Burton Act (LIBERTAD) passes both houses of U.S. Congress, further restricting Cuban trade embargo
1996 Movimiento Revolucionario Túpac Amaru (MRTA) forces storm the Japanese embassy in Perú and hold hostages
1994-1996 Peace accords between Guatemalan government and Unidad Revolucionaria Nacional Guatemalteca (URNG) signed
1993 North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) signed into law in the United States
1994 Aristide reinstalled as Haitian president due in part to international pressure
1998 Hugo Chavez elected president of Venezuela
1998 Augusto Pinochet arrested in London on charges of human rights violations
2000 Pinochet released from house arrest in the United Kingdom on medical grounds
2001 September 11 attacks in U.S. reorient Latin American policy towards counter terrorism
2002 U.S. Ambassador to the U.N. John Bolton implicates Cuba in Beyond the Axis of Evil speech
Collection Overview
The Washington Office on Latin America Records span the dates 1962 to 2008 and consist of research and project files on nearly every country in Latin America, administrative files, clippings, correspondence, and printed material, all related to the work of the Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA), a human rights advocacy organization based in Washington D.C. WOLA partners with local organizations in Latin America and the Caribbean to raise awareness of human rights abuses in the region and to influence the foreign policy agenda of the United States government. Materials in this collection provide a rich resource for the study of politically motivated violence and other human rights abuses throughout Latin America, and document the changing political attitudes towards the region on the part of the U.S. government over nearly four decades. Numerous files of individual human rights abuse cases, including torture, forced disappearances, and executions can be found in this collection. In addition, WOLA's efforts to lobby for legislative change are chronicled throughout the collection. Material includes some ephemeral or hard-to-find printed material produced by leftist or guerilla groups in Chile, Colombia, Guatemala, and Mexico, as well as some audiovisual recordings housed within country files.
The collection is arranged in the following series: Administrative Files, Geographic, Initiatives and Activities, Sound Recordings, and Oversize Material. The Administrative Files Series contains records kept by WOLA directors and staff, many funding-related files, some overviews of WOLA's activities, and other files of an administrative nature such as meeting minutes and planning, and staff retreats. The largest in the collection, the Geographic Series is divided into subseries for most countries in the region, documenting the major political and human rights issues associated with each country. These files typically include large sub-groupings on the following broad topics: human rights cases specific to that country; economic development; drug policy and related issues, especially in Colombia and Mexico; elections; police and military; U.S. policy; international relations; files related to WOLA visits to or activities in that country; and in some cases, files of printed materials assembled by WOLA staff. The human rights files cover such issues as labor rights, peasants' rights and land reforms, indigenous people's rights, politically motivated abuses, killings, and discrimination, civil rights cases of all kinds, reconciliation and truth commissions, and the activities of human rights organizations in each country and in the U.S. The Initiatives and Activities Series, divided into topical categories as arranged by WOLA staff, covers the organization's issue-based work in areas such as U.S. drug policy, trade and banking, democratic and peace processes, economic development, issues related to the deployment of military and police forces, and more. A large group of records documents the extensive legislative work performed by WOLA on behalf of human rights issues. There is considerable overlap between this series and the Geographic Series. The Sound Recordings Series contains recordings of conferences, speeches, and events sponsored by WOLA and other groups. Finally, the six boxes in the Oversize Material section at the end of this collection guide contain large items such as posters and newspapers separated from the main collection and rehoused for preservation purposes. Materials are chiefly in English and Spanish, with a smaller percentage in French and Portuguese. All of the series and each subseries are described in more detail in the description of the collection that follows. Unprocessed additions to the collection have been added at the end of the finding aid. Collection was acquired as part of the Duke University's Archive for Human Rights.
Conditions Governing Access note
Original audiovisual recordings are closed to research. Use copies must be made before contents can be accessed. Please contact the Research Services staff before coming to use these materials.
Related Material
Coletta Youngers Papers, 1977-2004 and undated, bulk 1983-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Global Rights Records, 1980-2006 and undated, bulk 1991-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 2017-0169 is closed until processing. This includes boxes 485-504.
Sound recordings; Human Rights -- Andes Region; Human Rights -- Argentina; Human Rights -- Central America; Human Rights -- Chile; Human Rights -- Colombia; Human Rights -- El Salvador; Human Rights -- Government policy -- United States; Human Rights -- Guatemala; Human Rights -- Haiti; Human Rights -- Latin America; Human Rights -- Mexico; Human Rights -- Mexico -- Chiapas; Human Rights -- Perú; Guatemala -- Economic conditions -- 1985-; Guatemala -- Politics and government -- 1985-; Guatemala -- Politics and government -- 1945-1985; Colombia -- Politics and government -- 1974-; Colombia -- Economic conditions -- 1970-; Chile -- Social conditions -- 1973-; Chile -- Politics and government -- 1973-; Chile -- History -- Coup d'état, 1973; Human rights advocacy -- United States; Human rights advocacy; Honduras -- Social conditions; Haiti -- Politics and government -- 1986-; Haiti -- Foreign relations -- United States; Guatemala -- Social conditions; Guatemala -- History -- Civil War, 1960-1996 -- Peace; Guatemala -- Foreign relations -- United States; Costa Rica -- Economic policy; Costa Rica -- Politics and government -- 1986-; Cuba -- Economic conditions -- 1990-; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1990-; Drug control -- United States; Drug control -- Latin America; El Salvador -- Social conditions; Economic development -- Latin America; Bolivia -- Economic conditions -- 1982-; Bolivia -- Politics and government -- 1982-; Brazil -- Politics and government -- 1985-2002; Brazil -- Politics and government -- 2003-2006; Argentina -- Social conditions -- 1983-; Colombia -- Social conditions -- 1970-; Argentina -- Politics and government -- 1983-2002; Mexico -- Politics and government; Nicaragua -- Politics and government -- 1990-; Latin America -- Politics and government -- 1980-; Latin America -- Social conditions; Peace-building -- Guatemala; Peru -- Politics and government -- 1980-; Panama -- Foreign relations -- United States; Peace-building -- Colombia; El Salvador -- Economic conditions -- 1945-; Human Rights -- Uruguay; El Salvador -- Politics and government -- 1979-1992; El Salvador -- Politics and government -- 1992-; Indigenous peoples -- Civil rights; Latin America -- Foreign relations -- United States; Human Rights -- Venezuela; Hurricane Mitch, 1998; United States -- Military policy; United States -- Foreign relations -- Latin America; United States -- Foreign relations -- Guatemala; United States -- Foreign relations -- Cuba; Video recordings; Venezuela -- Politics and government -- 1999-; Uruguay -- Politics and government -- 1985-; Uruguay -- Politics and government -- 1973-1985; Washington Office on Latin America; Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Administrative Files Series, 1968-2020; 1968-ongoing and undated, 43 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Documents a variety of administrative-level activities of the Washington Office on Latin America (WOLA) staff for almost the entirety of the organization's history up to 2007, with the majority of files representing the 1980s and 1990s. Organized into the following subseries: Development, Funding, General Management Files, Initiatives and Activities Office Files, and Publications. Arranged in original order as received, either unarranged, or in rough chronological or alphabetical order. See subseries descriptions below for details on contents and arrangement.
  - Development Subseries, 1979-2000 and undated, 5 boxes
    Documents pertaining to WOLA initiatives or projects to be funded. Includes targeted mailings; lists of contacts and prospects for funding; application materials and guidelines; grant proposals; newsletters and other publications regarding funding institutions; WOLA activity reports over a long time span; correspondence with funding institutions; and information on funding institutions regarding past grants. International donor files often contain copies of form letters relating to the Advocacy Training Project, while others contain larger amounts of materials such as reports, correspondence, follow-up material, and proposals. Other initiatives focus on violence against women (see the Liz Claiborne files, box 2), and drug policy work (Century Foundation Files, box 2). U.S. prospective donor files include information on Oxfam, Century Foundation, and the Greenville Foundation. Files retain arrangement and titles of folders as received from WOLA.
    - Development files (Box 1-5)
  - Funding Subseries, 1974-2005 and undated, 19 boxes
    Arranged in the following four subgroups: General Files, Appeals, Foundations, and Religious. Similar to the Development Subseries; contains folders pertaining chiefly to past contributors of grants or gifts to WOLA. See individual subgroup descriptions below.
    - General Files, 1983-2002 and undated (Box 6)
      Nine folders containing a variety of documents, including award notifications; drafts of form thank-you letters; lists/reports of donors, and related documents; correspondence and other documents related to contributing members of the fund-raising group "WOLA Friends;" notes, internal correspondence, results reports, and clippings regarding direct mailing campaigns and fund raising operations; a folder of notes and definitions regarding lobbying regulations; and copies of form letters soliciting funding from individual contributors and materials in support of these letters.
    - Appeals, 1987-1999 and undated (Box 6-7)
      Correspondence, clippings, draft letters, mailing lists, and other documents in support of periodic funding appeals to both individual donors and institutions; also includes annual reports and other funding activity summaries.
    - Foundations, 1978-2005 and undated (Box 7-17)
      Files on potential funding organizations or previous supporters contain correspondence, grant proposals and other supporting materials for applications, and other relevant documents, with some files related to specific WOLA projects. Folders are in a rough and repeating alphabetical order, grouped in date ranges. Prominent institutions represented include ARCA Foundation, Ford Foundation, General Service Foundation, Joyce Mertz-Gilmore Foundation, Ruth Mott Fund, J. Roderick MacArthur foundation, John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation, Oxfam, and Veatch Program (of the North Shore Unitarian Universalists).
    - Religious, 1974-2005 and undated (Box 17-24)
      Fund-raising files for both individuals and religious institutions, chiefly in the U.S., include correspondence, contact lists, summary reports on past funding, and other related documents. Institution files are in a rough and repeating alphabetical order, grouped into date ranges by year. In part due to its original religious orientation, many of WOLA's initiatives and activities have been sustained by the Methodist, Baptist, and Catholic churches, as well as other religious and spiritual groups such as Quakers and Unitarian Universalists.
  - General Management Files Subseries, 1968-2007 and undated, 15 boxes (Box 24-39)
    Series is organized into the following subgroupings: Director's Files, History Files, Other Organizations, Planning and Financial, Program Assistant Files, SAETH Files, Additional Files, Initiatives and Activities Office Files, and Publications. Includes information on organizational planning, including retreats; facilities (office space, computer systems, and telephone service); staff travel; management training; finances (tax returns, financial reports); working groups; staff meetings; personnel (manuals, regulations, staff member files and staff activity reports, vacancies and hiring); event planning; and public relations. The historical files were created by staff and contain varied materials documenting the history of WOLA from its beginning to 2003. The files from the Director's Office are chiefly from Alexander Wilde's tenure; these are varied in nature and include reports, files on events, notes on various topics, drafts of WOLA's mission statement, board member files, and internal and Congressional memos.
    - Director's Files, 1980s-1990s and undated, 4 boxes (Box 24-27)
      Extremely varied group of materials that were labeled as director's files and may have been maintained by a personal assistant to the directors. Includes correspondence, some of it to U.S. legislators; reports to and from the director; files on Central America, Europe, and countries related to WOLA activities; folders on notes on WOLA teams; WOLA event files; testimony files; delegations to countries; and other materials. One file labeled "Attacks" contains clippings and articles attacking WOLA and other organizations or movements considered liberal or left-wing.
    - History Files, 1974-2007 and undated, 4 boxes (Box 27-30)
      Offers a rich source of information on WOLA's origins and early years. Files pulled together by WOLA staff contain clippings and reports from the earliest years; mission statements; WOLA publications from the early 1980s, including a run of Update, WOLA's newsletter; flyers and other materials from the 10th (1984), 25th, and 30th anniversaries of WOLA's founding; a few annual reports from 1983 and later; detailed papers on WOLA's history and role in shaping U.S.-Latin American policy; early funding files relating to the Ford Foundation's early support of WOLA initiatives; a file on the "WOLA History Project," a proposal sent to the Ford Foundation in 2003 to document WOLA's history; and other materials. WOLA materials dating from the 1970s and 1980s may also be found in other series in the WOLA collection.
    - Other Organizations, 1986-1997, 3 boxes (Box 30-32)
      Files on other organizations supporting human rights causes, chiefly U.S.-based. Typically one folder per organization, but one set of multiple files relates to the Letelier-Moffitt Award. Arranged in alphabetical order. Abundant numbers of files on human rights organizations and their work are also found in the country files in the Geographical Series, and files throughout the collection.
    - Planning and Financial, 1968-2004, bulk 1990s-2004, 2 boxes (Box 32-33)
      A small group of planning files for WOLA events and proposals chiefly from the 1990s through 2004. Documents include correspondence, meeting agendas and notes, strategic planning notes, mission statements, and extensive descriptions of the functions of various working groups and their status at that time. A significant set of files documents a major WOLA planning retreat held in 2002, and discusses all aspects of its operations and programs. Also includes a large file of material on WOLA's efforts to gain consultative status with the United Nations. Other WOLA planning documents can be found scattered in other subseries in the Administrative Files, as well as other series in the collection, especially Initiatives and Activities. Tax returns and financial statements from 1979 through 2006 make up the bulk of the financial files.
    - Program Assistant Files, 1990-2006 and undated, 2 boxes (Box 33-34)
      As with the Director's Files, a varied set of office files created in support of key positions at WOLA. Most files date from the 2000s. Includes such material as memos, organizational lists, files of contacts, outreach files, web development, planning for events, WOLA reprints, and a few news clippings files dating from about 2006 on Haiti, Venezuela, and other countries and topics.
    - SAETH Files, 1989-2006 and undated, 3 boxes (Box 35-37)
      Documents relate to the activities of WOLA's South America and Economic Team working group, abbreviated to SAETH. Folders chiefly contain routine materials such as invitations to events, event planning, memos, press packets, training manuals and style guide, phone system files, and other office files.
    - Additional Files, 1982-2002 and undated, 4 boxes (Box 37-40)
      Files that could not be categorized in the groupings above include activity reports, WOLA Board documents, bylaws, contact lists, facilities and office systems documents, financial documents, intern files, lobbying regulations, personnel manuals, and staff writings.
  - Initiatives and Activities Office Files, 1989-2000 and undated, 3 boxes
    Files maintained by WOLA assistants concern the management of WOLA programs and activities, and contain memos, press releases, clippings, and other documents regarding human rights projects and responses undertaken by WOLA and its staff. The actual project files are housed in the much larger Initiatives and Activities Series.
    - Initiatives and activities files (Box 40-42)
  - Publications, 1991-2020; 1991-ongoing and undated, 2 boxes (Box 42-43)
    Production files for WOLA newsletters Cross Currents (English), and Enlace (Spanish). Folders contain proofs, notes, correspondence from readers, and other material. Some contain printed copies of the corresponding issue of the newsletters. See also the Geographic Series under individual countries or under the General Latin America Subseries for actual publication issues of many of WOLA's publications.
    - Publications (Box 42-43)
    - Venezuela Blog, 2012-2020; 2012-ongoing
    - Colombia Peace, 2013-2020; 2013-ongoing
    - Washington Office on Latin America Colombia Twitter, 2013
    - Adam Isacson Professional Twitter account, 2013
    - Washington Office on Latin America Twitter, 2012-2020; 2012-ongoing
    - Washington Office on Latin America website, 2011-2020; 2011-ongoing
    - Border Fact Check website, 2012-2020
- Geographic Series, 1962-2008 and undated, 250 boxes
  Files on individual countries in Latin America and the Caribbean, containing material assembled and maintained by the staff of the Washington Office on Latin America. Countries represented are: Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba, Ecuador, El Salvador, Guatemala, Guyana, Haiti, Honduras, Mexico, Nicaragua, Panama, Paraguay, Perú, Suriname, Uruguay, and Venezuela. The largest subseries are Chile, Colombia, Guatemala, Haiti, Mexico, and Perú. Most geographic files are a mix of documents created in each country and in the United States. Nearly all country subseries contain the following folder groups: Human Rights, U.S. Relations, and WOLA Files. Human Rights files document specific cases of abuse as well as some the organizations with which WOLA partners to improve the situation. U.S. Relations files, a major focus in each subseries, contain information on pending U.S. legislation, testimony before Congress, and files on the policy agendas of sitting administrations. WOLA files provide evidence of WOLA's diverse activities, including: organizing Congressional delegations to Latin American countries and visits to Washington D.C. for Latin American constituencies; organizing conferences and programs to increase dialogue and awareness of various concerns in Latin America; and efforts to influence the United States' foreign policy through lobbying. Larger subseries may have additional groups; common examples include Background Files, Economy and Development, Politics and Government, and Printed Material. With the exception of alphabetized printed material, the original order and organization of files has been maintained to the extent possible. A subseries on Latin America containing files that do not focus exclusively on one country completes the Geographic series. See subseries descriptions below for details on contents and arrangement.
  - Argentina, 1976-2004 and undated, 5 boxes